After what happened today,
Después de lo que pasó hoy,
we can be certain that Cui Jun
podemos confirmar que Cui Jun
wasn't abducted by Grand Tutor Xie.
no fue secuestrado por el Ministro Xie.
Otherwise,
De lo contrario,
he wouldn't have made a deal with me
no habría hecho un trato conmigo
just because of a letter from my mother.
solo por una carta de mi madre.
If Cui Jun were in his hands,
Si Cui Jun estuviera en su poder
he could have simply grilled him
y él quisiera saber la verdad del caso An y Lu,
for the truth behind the An and Lu families' case.
podría haberlo torturado directamente.
I know your little brain has become much sharper than before,
Sé que tu cabecita funciona mucho mejor que antes,
but it needs some rest now.
pero ahora necesita descansar.
Stop thinking about it.
No pienses más.
Yummy.
Está rico.
Back when we were on the march,
Antes, cuando estaba en campaña,
all we could eat were flatbreads or dried meat,
solo comía pan o carne seca.
and occasionally finding some wild greens would satisfy our cravings.
De vez en cuando encontraba verduras silvestres y ya era un lujo.
Now that you don't have much of an appetite
Ahora que no tienes apetito
and can't eat meat while in mourning,
y que por el luto no puedes comer carne,
you could try this first.
mejor prueba esto.
I've had wild-green flatbreads before,
También he comido tortitas de verduras silvestres,
but I've never had ones this delicious.
pero nunca tan buenas como estas.
Surely Qing Long couldn't have made these.
Seguro que Qing Long no las hace.
Please thank Yan Yue for me.
Dale las gracias de mi parte a Yan Yue.
Okay.
Bien.
You are Crown Prince Wenxi.
Tú eres el Príncipe Heredero Wenxi.
In terms of blood relations,
Por lazos de sangre,
you should be
deberías ser la persona
the person closest to my mother in this world.
más cercana a mi madre en este mundo.
Emperor Wenxi was my mother's elder brother,
El emperador Wenxi era hermano de mi madre,
so you should call her...
así que deberías llamarla...
Aunt.
Tía.
But compared to me,
Pero comparada conmigo,
even though you aren't Princess Yunzhao's biological daughter,
aunque no eres hija biológica de tu madre,
you are her true family.
eres su verdadera familia.
There's no need for you to tell me that.
No hace falta que me lo digas.
Blood ties are merely where one comes from,
Los lazos de sangre solo indican de dónde vienes,
but not where one belongs.
no a dónde perteneces.
A marriage brought about by the pressure of the imperial family,
El matrimonio impuesto por la presión de la familia real,
and one that had to be maintained in order to bind the aristocratic clans
mantenido solo para conectar a las familias nobles
and the imperial family together,
con el clan real,
ultimately wasted half the lives of both Princess Yunzhao and Grand Tutor.
al final desperdició media vida de la condesa y del ministro.
I hope that this time,
Espero que esta vez
you can help Princess Yunzhao find the freedom she deserved.
puedas conseguir la libertad para la condesa.
You sure sound convincing,
Hablas muy bien,
yet you're not exactly any better yourself.
pero tú no lo entiendes de verdad.
What?
¿Qué?
I mean,
Dije que,
without any witnesses,
si no hay testigos,
how can we bring the murderer
¿cómo se puede
who killed my mother to justice?
llevar ante la justicia al asesino de mi madre?
Isn't there already a rumor going around
¿No dicen todos que
that I killed Princess Yunzhao to seize the Phoenix Heart Token?
maté a la condesa para quedarme con la llave del corazón del fénix?
Let's fan the flames.
Pues que el fuego arda aún más fuerte.
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[Llave del Corazón del Fénix]
[Episode 18]
[Episodio 18]
Since I harboured prejudices against the An and Lu families,
Por tener prejuicios contra los clanes An y Lu,
I never truly listened to what was in your heart,
nunca escuché realmente tu voz
♪ I traded obsession for this loss ♪
♪ Con terquedad perdí lo que gané ♪
thinking it was merely your obsession.
y creí que solo era tu obsesión.
♪ If I could lay my heart bare and cross ♪
♪ Si este corazón pudiera abrir ♪
I always firmly believed that you were the one who had wronged me,
Siempre creí que fuiste tú quien me falló,
♪ Would you once more have pity on me ♪
♪ ¿Me darías otra vez tu compasión? ♪
but I never realized that I had wronged you as well.
pero no pensé que yo también te había fallado a ti.
I suspect that 25 years ago,
Sospecho que hace 25 años
♪ If the heavens should change and fate tear me apart ♪
♪ Si el cielo cambia y el destino me rompe ♪
the real Cui Jun had already been killed,
el verdadero Cui Jun ya fue asesinado,
♪ Yet still cannot undo one beat of my heart's art ♪
♪ Pero no apaga ni un segundo de extrañarte ♪
and that the man who survived was a secret agent from Northern Qin.
y el que vivió después era un espía de Beiqin.
If that's the case, then perhaps there's more to
Entonces el caso An y Lu que él denunció
♪ I've traveled so far— the day I find you again ♪
♪ Anduve tanto, el día que te reencuentre ♪
the An and Lu families' crime he exposed back then than meets the eye.
podría tener otra historia.
♪ I fear you might have forgotten me ♪
♪ Temo que me hayas olvidado ♪
He refuses to speak now,
Ahora se niega a hablar,
but I've brought him back to Jiankang.
pero lo he traído de vuelta a Jiankang.
♪ I fear no doom of endless karmic pain ♪
♪ No me da miedo caer en la perdición ♪
Whether or not I can clear the An and Lu families' name,
Ya sea que pueda demostrar la inocencia de An y Lu o no,
♪ Only that you drift far from my side ♪
♪ Solo temo que te alejes ♪
at least this time,
Al menos esta vez
♪ Apart from you, the world is an endless night ♪
♪ Cuando me alejo de ti, el mundo se sumerge en una noche eterna ♪
I'm standing with you.
estoy de tu lado.
♪ Even if my beating heart wears thin and fades ♪
♪ Aunque el latido al fin desfallezca ♪
We were once husband and wife.
Fuimos esposos una vez.
May all past grievances be laid to rest,
Espero que de ahora en adelante se acaben los rencores
♪ I'd choose this fate till death's final line ♪
♪ Moriré de buena gana ♪
and may you no longer be trapped by the past.
y que tú no sigas atrapado en el pasado.
♪ I only hope the mortal lands ♪
♪ Solo espero que este mundo ♪
♪ Can grant our wishes ♪
♪ Haga realidad nuestros deseos ♪
♪ Through endless night, let heaven and earth fall apart ♪
♪ A través de la noche eterna, aunque el cielo y la tierra se destruyan ♪
♪ Just to gaze upon you one last time ♪
♪ Para volver a verte una vez más ♪
Grand Tutor.
Ministro.
I told you
Te conté
about Li Mao's background
el origen de Li Mao
to warn you about the situation,
para advertirte de la situación,
not so you could
¡no para que
kill my wife!
mataras a mi esposa!
You're the one who truly fails to understand the situation!
Quien realmente no entiende la situación eres tú.
Crown Prince Wenxi isn't dead at all,
El Príncipe Heredero Wenxi no murió.
and they still have the Phoenix Heart Token!
Ellos todavía tienen la llave del corazón del fénix.
What did you say?
¿Qué dices?
If Princess Yunzhao had returned alive,
Si la condesa volvía viva,
my brother would have had no chance of survival.
mi hermano no tendría ninguna posibilidad de sobrevivir.
What other option did I have?
¿Qué podía hacer?
I wouldn't spare anyone
No tendré piedad con nadie
who might pose a threat to him.
que pueda amenazarlo.
Grand Tutor.
Ministro.
Mao.
Hermano.
Let's go.
Vamos.
What's this supposed to mean?
¿Qué es esto?
I said I'd give you this as a gift.
Es lo que te iba a regalar.
It's made of black iron, which is even tougher than refined iron.
Es metal negro, más resistente que el hierro refinado,
It won't rust or corrode for 100 years,
no se oxida ni se corroe en cien años,
and it's 100 times more powerful than Eagle King's Longque Blade.
y es cien veces más poderoso que Longque del Rey Águila.
When did you forge it?
¿Cuándo lo forjaste?
Before we left for Guazhou.
Antes de ir a Guazhou.
But it didn't have a scabbard back then.
Pero entonces no tenía vaina.
I specifically asked
Pedí especialmente
Master Wei from Yunyan Pavilion
al maestro Wei de la Torre Yunyan
to craft one for this sword.
que hiciera una vaina para esta espada.
Well? Do you like it?
¿Qué te parece? ¿Te gusta?
I'm sure
Supongo que
you wouldn't just give this to me for nothing.
no será tan fácil que me la regales, ¿verdad?
By the banks of the Qushui River, there's a mountain called Mount Fengming.
Al lado del río Qu hay una montaña llamada Monte Fénix Cantor.
It offers a broad view,
Desde allí la vista es amplia.
and when the weather is clear,
Cuando hace buen tiempo,
you can see the rolling mountain ranges.
se ven las montañas que se extienden sin fin.
Behind those ranges
Detrás de esas montañas,
lies my mother's former fief,
está el antiguo feudo de mi madre,
Yunzhao Prefecture.
el Condado Yun Zhao.
Though, unfortunately, it later fell under the control of Northern Qin.
Lástima que ahora pertenece a Beiqin.
So?
¿Entonces?
So I want to buy this mountain
Entonces quiero comprar esa montaña
and make it my mother's burial site.
para hacer la tumba de mi madre.
However,
Pero
it is currently owned by a wealthy local family,
ahora está en manos de un rico local,
and they're asking for a very high price.
y el precio es muy alto.
I've scraped together what I can,
Junté mi dinero
but I'm still short by this little bit.
y todavía me falta un poco.
Don't worry, I'm not borrowing it for free.
No te preocupes, no te lo pido gratis,
I've already paid you interest.
ya te he dado los intereses.
How much are you short?
¿Cuánto te falta?
Five thousand taels.
Cinco mil taeles.
Don't tell me
¿Cómo es posible?
that the dignified Heir of Prince Jing'an, commander of Beifu,
¿El heredero del Rey Jing'an, comandante de Beifu,
can't even come up with
no puede reunir
a mere 5,000 taels.
ni cinco mil taeles?
My father owns a small forested mountain on the outskirts of the capital.
Mi padre tiene una pequeña colina en las afueras de la capital,
The fengshui there is no worse than that of Mount Fengming.
con mejor feng shui que el Monte Fénix Cantor.
I'd be happy to gift it to Princess Yunzhao.
Estoy dispuesto a regalárselo a la condesa.
If you don't want to lend it, just say so.
Si no quieres prestar, está bien.
Why go to all that trouble with lies?
¿Para qué tantas mentiras?
Your Highness, why did you suddenly decide to clean the horse today?
Su Alteza, ¿por qué quiere lavar el caballo hoy?
Your Highness, it's all here.
Su Alteza, aquí está todo.
You've invested all your personal savings in the army,
Usted ha invertido todo su dinero en el ejército,
leaving only this small amount on you.
solo le quedan estos.
It's only a bit over 3,000 taels.
Son más de tres mil taeles.
The dignified Heir of Prince Jing'an
El heredero del Rey Jing'an
only has 3,000 taels of personal savings—
solo tiene tres mil taeles en su bolsillo,
no one would believe that if word got out.
nadie lo creería.
Sell this red steed,
Vende este caballo.
then exchange all of this for cash
Cambia todo esto por plata en efectivo,
and give it to He Yuanji.
y dáselo a He Yuanji.
Have her withdraw my entire share
Que saque también mi parte
from the family estate
de dinero de la mansión,
and give it all to Xie Jiayu.
y que se lo entregue todo a Xie Jiayu,
Just tell her it's a loan from the Prince's household.
diciéndole que es un préstamo de la mansión real.
But this is the prized Western Regions steed your father, His Highness, gave you,
Pero es el caballo de la Región Occidental que su padre le regaló a usted.
1 in 10,000.
Un corcel excepcional.
You won't find another one like it in all of Ye.
No hay otro igual en todo Ye.
You wouldn't even bear to ride it onto the battlefield.
Ni siquiera quería montarlo en batalla.
Sell it.
Véndelo.
Why didn't you try to talk him out of it?
Convéncelo.
Why should I?
¿Para qué?
Everything in this world has a price, but affection is priceless.
Todo tiene precio, solo el amor no tiene precio.
Don't you know what matters more
¿No sabes lo que pesa más
in His Highness's heart?
en el corazón del heredero?
Back when he used to toss money to Master Yuan,
Antes, cuando le dábamos dinero al maestro Yuan,
at least you could hear it clink.
al menos hacía ruido.
Now he doesn't even reveal his name.
Ahora ni siquiera aparece el nombre.
You fool.
Eres tonto.
Can't you think of a way
¿No sabes hacer que
to let Lady Xie know?
la señorita Xie lo sepa?
Lady Xie?
¿La señorita Xie?
I heard that when I was severely injured after receiving a flogging,
He oído que cuando estuve gravemente enfermo por el castigo de los azotes,
it was Your Highness who paid for the purchase of precious medicinal herbs
fue usted quien pagó de su propio bolsillo las costosas medicinas
to treat me.
para curarme,
It must have cost Your Highness a lot.
y que el gasto fue considerable.
Since I can't pay you back right now,
Ahora no puedo pagarlo.
I offer this deed of debt
Aquí tiene este pagaré
as proof
como prueba.
that I'll surely repay the debt someday.
Algún día se lo devolveré.
It was merely a small favor.
Fue solo un pequeño gesto.
One should not accept rewards without merit.
No acepto favores sin merecerlos.
The life-saving kindness Your Highness has shown me is far too great.
Consorte, me salvó la vida, es una deuda demasiado grande.
A great favor can become a burden like an enemy's debt.
Una gran deuda es como una ofensa.
I'd rather bear a debt
Prefiero deber dinero
than carry the weight of your kindness.
a deber favores.
Sorry for offending you that day.
Aquel día fui grosero.
The distinction between nobles and commoners and the differences in people's hearts...
La diferencia entre clases, la diferencia entre corazones.
You aristocratic traitors—
¡Las familias nobles están vendiendo el país!
you're parasites feeding off our country!
¡Son gusanos del país!
Are not something a woman like Your Highness could overcome.
Eso no es algo que una mujer como usted pueda cambiar.
I shouldn't have taken my anger out on Your Highness.
No debí desquitarme con usted.
I hereby apologize to Your Highness.
Le pido disculpas.
How do you plan
Con tanto dinero,
to pay this much money back?
¿cómo piensas devolvérmelo?
By copying books, or selling my calligraphy—
Copiando libros, vendiendo caligrafía.
I'll find a way.
Siempre hay manera.
Let's go.
Vamos.
Qing Long?
¿Qing Long?
Why are you taking the red steed out of the mansion?
¿Por qué sacas este caballo de la mansión?
His Highness asked me to sell it.
El heredero me pidió que lo vendiera.
Sell it?
¿Venderlo?
Yes. His Highness told me not to say anything.
Sí, pero el heredero dijo que no se lo contara a nadie.
Please pretend you didn't see it, Your Highness.
Consorte, por favor, haga como que no lo vio.
Nanxing.
Nanxing,
bring out my short dagger.
saca mi cuchillo corto.
My Lady,
Señorita,
but Her Highness
pero ese es
left it to you for self-defense.
el que la condesa le dejó para defenderse.
I've got no choice. I'm broke.
Soy pobre.
Take these out and ask around how much they're worth.
Lleva todo esto afuera para preguntar el precio.
If the price is reasonable, just pawn them all.
Véndelo todo si el precio es justo.
I'll figure out a way to make up the rest.
Lo que falte, pensaré cómo conseguirlo.
If we pawn Miraculous Craft as well,
Si hipoteco la Tienda Mano Maravillosa,
it should probably be enough.
quizás ya llegue.
Is His Highness really unwilling to lend you the money?
¿El heredero realmente no quiso prestar el dinero?
That's really stingy of him.
Qué tacaño.
He's the commander of Beifu, after all.
Es comandante de Beifu.
Didn't he just confiscate the Cui family's mines?
¿Y no acaba de confiscar las minas de la familia Cui?
Those were confiscated on behalf of the court.
Eso fue para la corte,
They're not the Xiao family's private property.
no es propiedad privada de los Xiao.
Still, I never expected
Pero también me sorprende que
Xiao Wuyi wouldn't even lend me 5,000 taels.
Xiao Wuyi no me prestara ni cinco mil taeles.
I thought he would at least...
Creí que al menos…
Xie Jiayu,
Xie Jiayu,
I'm smitten with you.
te quiero.
Talking about being smitten with me.
¿Que me quiere?
Forget it.
Bueno,
In the end, I only have myself to rely on.
al final tengo que depender de mí misma.
Yuanji.
Yuanji.
This is...
Esto...
I'm lending this to you on behalf of Prince Jing'an's Household.
Es lo que la mansión te presta.
Take it and choose any place you like
Puedes elegir el lugar que más te guste
as Princess Yunzhao's burial site.
para la condesa.
The Heir has been fighting battles all over the country these past years.
El heredero ha estado años en batalla,
Although he hasn't spent much on himself,
gasta poco para sí mismo,
Beifu's expenditures have been enormous.
pero Beifu consume mucho.
He's poured all his salary into the army.
Todo su salario lo ha invertido en el ejército.
The expenses of Prince Jing'an's Household
Los gastos de la Mansión del Rey Jing'an
have been completely supported by me and the Princess Consort.
los cubrimos la reina y yo,
We truly cannot count on the Heir and Prince Jing'an.
no podemos contar con el heredero ni con su padre.
I oversee Prince Jing'an's Household's accounts,
Yo llevo las cuentas de la Mansión del Rey Jing'an.
and the Heir is indeed short on funds.
El heredero sí está corto de dinero,
I'm being completely honest.
puedo decirte la verdad.
Then where did this money come from?
¿Y entonces de dónde salió este dinero?
The Heir had Ferghana horse.
El heredero tenía un caballo,
I heard it was a gift from Prince Jing'an
se dice que fue el regalo de su padre
when he won his first battle.
tras su primera victoria en la batalla.
That horse had a pure bloodline and was priceless.
Ese caballo tiene pura sangre y es valioso.
A few days ago, I saw Qing Long
Hace unos días vi a Qing Long
lead it away to be sold,
sacarlo para venderlo.
along with some land deeds and shop deeds.
También algunas escrituras de tierras y tiendas,
All together, this is how much was raised.
juntando todo, llegó a esta cantidad.
The Heir even kept it from me too.
El heredero incluso me lo ocultó.
He only told me to send the money over.
Solo me pidió que te trajera el dinero.
Do you know what the two largest expenses
¿Sabes cuáles han sido
under the Heir's name in the household
los dos mayores gastos a nombre del heredero
were in the past year?
en el último año?
What?
¿Cuáles?
The first was your wedding with the Heir—
El primero fue tu boda con el heredero.
a fake wedding doomed to be ruined from the start.
Una boda falsa que estaba destinada a fracasar.
Well, a fake act has to be made
Pero para que la farsa
convincing enough for people to believe it, right?
fuera creíble, había que hacerla bien.
The second was the renovation
El segundo fue la reconstrucción
of this Cangfeng Forge after you moved into the mansion.
de esta Forja Cangfeng después de que llegaste.
This place used to be nothing more than
Aquí antes era solo
an empty room for storing sundries,
un cuarto de trastos,
abandoned for years.
abandonado durante años.
Didn't you notice
¿No te has dado cuenta de que
that the furnace outside was also renovated?
también reconstruyeron el horno de fuera?
No wonder.
Con razón.
No wonder it looks so much like the one at my home.
Por eso se parece tanto al de mi casa.
Xiao Wuyi,
Xiao Wuyi.
you sold your horse,
Vendiste tu caballo
but you didn't take the interest.
pero no te llevaste los intereses.
Qing Long...
Este Qing Long…
But this is not
Pero lo que quiero
what I want.
no es esto.
What do you want then?
¿Qué es lo que quieres?
I'm not telling you.
No te lo voy a decir.
I don't want you to think of this
No quiero que creas que
as a transaction.
esto es un trato.
Your Highness.
Su Alteza,
The Empress Dowager is hosting a banquet.
la Emperatriz Suprema da un banquete en el palacio.
Under what pretext?
¿Con qué motivo?
She claims
Dijo que
Empress Wenxi
la emperatriz Wenxi
appeared in her dream,
se le apareció en sueños
asking Your Highness to bring the Phoenix Heart Token into the palace.
y le pidió que usted lleve la llave del corazón del fénix al palacio.
All right.
Bien.
She finally couldn't hold back any longer
Al final no pudo contenerse
and came forward on her own.
y se ha delatado.
Mother!
¡Madre!
Why do people like you, high and mighty,
¿Por qué ustedes, los que están arriba,
always try to corner me and my brother?
siempre disfrutan presionándonos a mi hermano y a mí?
We simply want to survive.
Solo queremos sobrevivir.
Your Highness.
Su Alteza.
My brother has been so kind to Yaoyao.
Mi hermano ha sido tan bueno con Yaoyao.
Why are you still unwilling to let him go?
¿Por qué no lo dejas en paz?
Calm down!
¡Cálmate!
I never wanted Prince Qi dead!
Yo nunca he querido la muerte del Príncipe Qi.
You hold the Phoenix Heart Token,
Tienes la llave del corazón del fénix
and you intend to support Crown Prince Wenxi.
y quieres apoyar al Príncipe Heredero Wenxi.
If he ever makes it to Jiankang,
Si algún día llega a Jiankang,
will my brother have any chance of survival?
¿mi hermano tendrá alguna posibilidad de vivir?
Tell me,
Dime,
where exactly is Crown Prince Wenxi hiding?
¿dónde está escondido el Príncipe Heredero Wenxi?
There's no way I'll tell you that!
No puedo decírtelo.
Fine. Then let's take this secret with us
Bien, entonces
and vanish
desaparezcamos juntas
from this world together!
con este secreto.
Mao...
Hermano.
Lejun.
Lejun,
Don't be afraid.
no tengas miedo.
Mao...
Hermano.
Mao.
Hermano,
Do you remember
¿recuerdas
when we were little,
cuando éramos niños
wandering among displaced refugees?
y nos mezclábamos entre los refugiados?
Back then,
En ese momento,
whenever there was a single flatbread
siempre que había un pan
or a bowl of porridge,
o un tazón de gachas,
you'd always let me have it.
tú me lo dabas a mí primero.
Whenever older children tried to bully me,
Cuando los niños mayores querían pegarme,
you'd risk your life to protect me.
tú me protegías con tu vida.
Those memories aren't pleasant.
Esos recuerdos no son buenos,
I've long forgotten them.
yo no los recuerdo.
But I haven't.
Pero yo sí.
Although those days were harsh,
Aunque aquellos días fueron duros,
they were the happiest time
para mí
of my life.
fueron felices,
Because even back then,
porque desde entonces supe que
I knew I had the best older brother in the entire world—
tenía al mejor hermano del mundo.
one who'd never let go of my hand,
Nunca soltarías mi mano
not even in death.
ni aunque murieras.
Mao.
Hermano,
I wasn't afraid then,
en ese entonces no tuve miedo,
and I'm even less afraid now.
ahora menos.
Mao.
Hermano,
I will protect you, no matter what.
yo te protegeré.
It's alright.
Ya pasó.
Don't be afraid.
No tengas miedo.
Yaoyao.
Yaoyao.
Greetings, Princess Pingning.
Saludo a la Vizcondesa Pingning.
Are you truly determined
¿de verdad
to draw a line between us?
vas a distanciarte de mí?
Her Highness...
La condesa...
Other than an admission of guilt,
Aparte de una confesión de culpa,
I never want to hear another word
no quiero volver a oír nada
about my mother from your lips.
sobre mi madre de tus labios.
We were once good friends.
Fuimos amigas.
There's no need for such hollow pretenses between us.
¿Para qué estas falsedades?
Yaoyao.
Yaoyao,
You've truly grown up.
has crecido.
It's all because of you that I had to grow up.
Ustedes son los que me han obligado a crecer.
Do you really think
¿Crees que lo hiciste
your scheme was flawless?
todo perfecto?
That day,
Aquel día
Her Highness and I both fell off the cliff.
caí por el acantilado junto con la condesa.
If not for a tree that caught me,
Si no me hubiera enganchado un árbol,
I wouldn't have survived, either.
también habría muerto.
And it was Young Lord Xiao's men saved me.
Fueron los hombres del heredero Xiao quienes me rescataron.
M-My hand had only just healed.
Mi mano acaba de sanar.
To accuse me of trying to harm Princess Yunzhao
Decir que yo quería matar a la condesa
is rather absurd.
es absurdo.
If that's the case,
Entonces,
then why did you have Da snatch the coachman's family
¿por qué mandaste a Da a quitarme
from me?
a la familia del mozo de cuadra?
Were you afraid
¿Tienes miedo de que
they witnessed something they shouldn't have?
realmente hayan visto algo?
But they didn't see anything.
Pero no vieron nada.
Lejun.
Lejun,
I truly hope it wasn't you.
realmente esperaba que no fueras tú,
Because if it was,
porque si fueras así,
I'd be deeply disappointed in our friendship.
me decepcionaría mucho de la amistad.
Yaoyao.
Yaoyao.
I didn't expect you to enter the palace today.
No esperaba que vinieras hoy al palacio.
Mao.
Mao,
You knew I was using you
sabías que estaba usándote
to test Li Lejun.
para probar a Li Lejun.
She's your sister.
Ella es tu hermana.
I believe you only learned about it afterwards.
Creo que te enteraste después.
I understand that you were put in a difficult position.
Entiendo que estás en una situación difícil,
I don't blame you.
no te culpo.
But please, don't make things difficult for me anymore either.
Pero te pido que tampoco me pongas a mí en más aprietos.
Long live Your Majesty!
¡Larga vida a la Emperatriz Suprema!
You may rise, my beloved ministers.
Levántense, todos.
Thank you, Your Majesty!
Gracias, Su Majestad.
Today, at this palace banquet,
Hoy celebramos un banquete en el palacio.
I'd like to raise a toast with all my beloved ministers.
Brindo con todos ustedes.
A few days ago, Empress Wenxi appeared to me in a dream,
Hace unos días, la emperatriz Wenxi se me apareció en sueños
and I've learned that the old prophecy—
y supe que el antiguo dicho
"when the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world"—
"cuando aparezca la llave del corazón del fénix, el mundo se unificará"
is no mere tale.
era cierto.
Two Phoenix Heart Tokens have been
Hay dos llaves del corazón del fénix,
passed down to Princess Yunzhao and Cui Jun respectively.
una entregada a la condesa y otra a Cui Jun.
That's enough.
Basta.
My Lord,
Señor,
what's the point of arresting me?
¿para qué me arrestas?
I'm a useless wreck now.
Ya soy un inútil.
The Phoenix Heart Token is in Xiao Wuyi's hands.
La llave del corazón del fénix está en manos de Xiao Wuyi.
Young Lord Xiao.
Heredero Xiao,
It's been quite some time since you returned from Guazhou.
hace tiempo que volviste de Guazhou.
When will the convicted criminal Cui be transferred to the Court of Judicial Review?
¿Cuándo vas a entregar al prisionero de la familia Cui al Tribunal Supremo?
And where is the Phoenix Heart Token?
¿Y dónde está la llave del corazón del fénix?
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad,
Cui Jun was abducted.
Cui Jun fue secuestrado.
When did this happen?
¿Cuándo ocurrió?
And where was he abducted?
¿Dónde fue secuestrado?
It was 5 days ago.
Hace cinco días.
I'm still searching for him.
Yo también lo estoy buscando.
He was abducted 5 days ago,
Se escapó hace cinco días.
so why didn't you report it?
¿Por qué no lo has informado?
Do you have any regard for the laws of Ye?
¿Acaso no tienes respeto por la ley de Ye?
Or could it be that
¿O es que tú mismo
you hid Cui Jun away yourself—
lo escondiste,
just like how you silenced Princess Yunzhao
igual que silenciaste a la condesa
and stole her Phoenix Heart Token?
y le robaste su llave del corazón del fénix?
Vice Minister Qi, you seem eager to pin a crime on me.
Viceministro Qi, ¿tan rápido quieres culparme?
I have long submitted a memorial confessing my fault
Ya presenté el informe de la pérdida de Cui Jun
over Cui Jun's disappearance.
hace tiempo.
Deliver this memorial to the Department of State Affairs.
Lleva el informe de autocrítica al Ministerio de Asuntos de Estado.
Remember, slip it in among the daily greetings memorials
Mézclalo entre los informes de saludos,
so it draws no attention.
que no llame la atención.
Understood.
Sí.
I know the Cui Family Case is of great importance,
Yo sé que el caso de la familia Cui es grave,
but I haven't heard anything from the Department of State Affairs.
pero el Ministerio de Asuntos de Estado no ha dado respuesta.
I was wondering myself—
También me pregunto
how is it that Cui Jun has disappeared,
por qué la corte no se preocupa
yet the court doesn't seem concerned at all?
por la desaparición de Cui Jun.
As a witness in the Cui Family Case,
Como testigo del caso de la familia Cui,
I've been waiting for the court deliberation.
todavía estoy esperando la deliberación en la corte.
Vice Minister Qi.
Viceministro Qi,
You've gone and accused me of silencing Princess Yunzhao.
dices que yo maté a la condesa.
Do you have any evidence?
¿Tienes pruebas?
Might I charge you with lodging a false accusation?
¿Puedo considerar esto una calumnia?
You...
Tú...
Anyway, Cui Jun disappeared while he was in your custody.
De todos modos, Cui Jun se perdió en tus manos.
Enough. You are both loyal and righteous ministers.
Bueno, ustedes dos son ministros leales.
There is no need to blame each other.
No se culpen mutuamente.
Your Majesty, what I mean is that
Su Majestad, creo que
Young Lord Xiao deliberately concealed the Phoenix Heart Token's whereabouts.
Xiao Wuyi ha ocultado deliberadamente la llave del corazón del fénix.
Now that Princess Yunzhao fell dead
Ahora la condesa muere repentinamente,
and Cui Jun has disappeared without a trace,
y Cui Jun desaparece.
if it weren't for Empress Wenxi appearing to you in a dream,
Si usted no hubiera tenido el sueño de la emperatriz Wenxi,
we would all
me temo que todos nosotros
remain kept in the dark by him.
habríamos sido engañados.
I believe there's definitely more to
Creo que la muerte de la condesa
Princess Yunzhao's death than meets the eye.
tiene algo raro.
I respectfully request that Your Majesty conduct a thorough investigation.
Solicito una investigación exhaustiva.
Grand Tutor Xie.
Ministro Xie,
Since Vice Minister Qi insists
El viceministro Qi insiste
there's more to Princess Yunzhao's death,
en que la muerte de la condesa tiene algo raro.
would you support a thorough investigation
¿Apoyaría usted una investigación exhaustiva
to seek justice for Princess Yunzhao?
para hacerle justicia?
If there is evidence,
Si hay pruebas,
then naturally it should be investigated.
hay que investigar.
Since this is merely an accusation
Si solo son palabras
with no evidence,
sin fundamento,
let's put the matter of Princess Yunzhao aside for now.
dejemos el asunto de la condesa en pausa.
Young Lord Xiao.
Heredero Xiao,
Do you have Cui Jun's Phoenix Heart Token in your possession?
¿la llave del corazón del fénix de Cui Jun está en tus manos?
Don't tell me it was snatched away
¿No la habrán robado
along with Cui Jun when he was abducted.
junto con Cui Jun?
No, it wasn't.
No.
The Phoenix Heart Token
La llave del corazón del fénix
is indeed in my possession.
está en mis manos.
So it's in his possession?
¿Está en sus manos?
Is that the Phoenix Heart Token?
¿Esa es la llave del corazón del fénix?
Everyone, please take a look.
Miren, todos.
This is the Phoenix Heart Token that Cui Jun had.
Esta es la llave del corazón del fénix que tenía Cui Jun.
So this is the Phoenix Heart Token?
Esta es la llave del corazón del fénix.
I wonder if when Empress Wenxi appeared in your dream,
Me pregunto si es la misma que la emperatriz Wenxi
was this the piece she showed you, Your Majesty?
mostró a usted en sus sueños, Su Majestad.
Since you all wish to see it so badly,
Ya que todos quieren verla,
why not pass it around?
que circule.
It doesn't seem all that special.
No parece nada especial.
Isn't this just an ordinary token? How could it deserve the saying
Es solo una llave común.
"when the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world"?
¿Cómo puede ser "cuando aparezca la llave, el mundo se asentará"?
It is said the Cui family's private mines
Se dice que la mina privada de la familia Cui
were discovered because of this Phoenix Heart Token.
se descubrió por esta llave del corazón del fénix.
In your opinion, Young Lord Xiao,
Heredero Xiao,
after Cui Jun has finally been brought to justice
Cui Jun cometió muchos delitos,
after having committed countless crimes, who should this Token be handed over to?
después de que él sea juzgado, ¿a quién debería entregarse esta llave?
Did Empress Wenxi not mention this
¿La emperatriz Wenxi no mencionó nada
to Your Majesty when she appeared in your dream?
en sus sueños, Su Majestad?
"Under Heaven,
Bajo el cielo,
all land belongs to the ruler;
todo es tierra del emperador,
within the realm,
en toda la tierra,
all people are the ruler's subjects.
todos son súbditos del emperador.
Yet unfair divisions burden the officials,
Pero si los ministros no son justos,
while I alone toil tirelessly.
yo solo tengo que esforzarme.
Praise that I am not yet worn with age,
Aún no soy viejo,
still strong and vigorous.
estoy en la plenitud de mi fuerza,
With robust strength, I oversee all corners of the realm."
dispuesto a gobernar en todas direcciones.
I hope Your Majesty will have sympathy for the Beifu troops
Su Majestad, le pido que comprenda el sacrificio
who fight without regard for their lives,
de los soldados del ejército de Beifu
yet suffer from shoddy weaponry.
y su preocupación por las armas defectuosas.
I respectfully request that the copper and iron mines
Que los minerales de cobre y hierro
confiscated from the Cui family's private mines
confiscados de la mina privada de la familia Cui
be allocated to the Beifu Army
se entreguen al ejército de Beifu
to upgrade their armaments.
para mejorar su armamento.
Please rise, Young Lord Xiao.
Levántate, heredero Xiao.
What you speak makes perfect sense.
Lo que has dicho tiene razón.
The Beifu soldiers are warriors of our great Ye.
Los soldados de Beifu son de Ye.
I approved your Beifu Reform
Aprobé tu propuesta de la reforma de Beifu
precisely to forge a more elite, formidable army.
precisamente para tener mejores tropas.
Moreover, you've rendered meritorious service
Además, has hecho un gran servicio al investigar el caso Cui,
in cracking the Cui Family Case and deserve a reward.
mereces una recompensa.
I find your request
Me parece bien
most reasonable.
tu petición.
The Cui family's private mines shall be dedicated to
Que las minas de Cui se usen
upgrading the Beifu Army's weaponry.
para mejorar el armamento del ejército de Beifu.
On behalf of the Beifu soldiers,
En nombre de los soldados de Beifu,
I thank Your Majesty for your benevolent grace.
se lo agradezco, Su Majestad.
Xiao Wuyi!
Xiao Wuyi,
How dare you mock me?
¿te atreves a burlarte de mí?
Where's the Phoenix Heart Token?
¿Dónde está la llave del corazón del fénix?
How could this be?
¿Cómo puede ser?
How come it's empty?
¿Por qué está vacío?
I have no idea.
No lo sé.
The Phoenix Heart Token
Hace un momento la llave del corazón del fénix
was right here in this brocade box just moments ago.
estaba en este cofre.
All the officials in the court saw it.
Todos los ministros la vieron.
-Yeah, we all saw it. -How could it be gone?
La vimos todos. ¿Por qué desapareció?
There's no way.
Imposible.
Exactly.
Sí.
Everyone saw it. It needs to be thoroughly investigated.
Lo vimos. Hay que investigarlo a fondo.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad,
I noticed
hace un momento vi
that when His Highness turned around,
a la Vizcondesa Pingning robar la llave del corazón del fénix
Princess Pingning stole the Phoenix Heart Token.
cuando el heredero se giró.
I didn't! You're slandering me!
¡No es cierto! ¡Me estás calumniando!
Doing that in front of everyone here— do you think I'm crazy?
¿Acaso estoy tan loca como para hacer eso en público?
Whether you have it or not, we'll know after a search.
Si lo hiciste o no, con registrarte se sabrá.
Search her.
Registren.
Your Majesty!
Su Majestad.
I didn't...
No.
I didn't. I...
No, yo...
It was really on her. It really was.
¡Sí la tiene! ¡La tiene!
Your Majesty!
¡Su Majestad!
Your Majesty, that's impossible!
¡Su Majestad! ¡Es imposible!
I was framed.
Fui incriminada.
I-I didn't take it!
No tomé la llave.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad,
May I borrow the brocade box?
¿puedo tomar prestado el cofre?
Granted.
Sí.
There's a hidden compartment?
Hay un compartimento secreto.
You...
Tú...
That's right.
Sí.
You didn't take Cui Jun's token.
Es cierto que no tomaste la de Cui Jun.
Because the one that fell out of you
Porque la que cayó de tu ropa
was my mother's.
es de mi madre.
Princess Yunzhao's?
¿Es de la condesa?
Why did she have Princess Yunzhao's token?
¿Cómo puede ella tener la llave de la condesa?
Exactly.
Sí.
Please forgive me, Your Majesty,
Perdóneme, Su Majestad.
for contriving this contraption to conceal the Phoenix Heart Token
Hice este mecanismo para ocultar la llave del corazón del fénix
and deceiving you.
y engañarla a usted
I did so only to retrieve the token on Princess Pingning
solo para encontrar la llave que lleva la vizcondesa
and uncover the truth behind my mother's death.
y esclarecer la muerte de mi madre.
I'm innocent.
Soy inocente.
That Phoenix Heart Token didn't belong to Princess Yunzhao.
Esa llave del corazón del fénix no es de la condesa.
What makes you say so?
¿Por qué dices que no es?
Could it be that you've seen my mother's token?
¿Has visto la llave del corazón del fénix de mi madre?
When?
¿Cuándo?
Li Lejun.
Li Lejun,
You murdered Princess Yunzhao for the Phoenix Heart Token.
asesinaste a la condesa para obtener la llave del corazón del fénix.
The Phoenix Heart Token on you
La llave del corazón del fénix que tienes
is the most compelling evidence of your guilt.
es la mayor evidencia.
It's not like that.
No es así.
It's not...
No.
It seems
Parece que
Princess Yunzhao's death is indeed suspicious.
la muerte de la condesa sí es sospechosa.
It's fake.
Es falsa.
That Phoenix Heart Token is fake.
Esa llave del corazón del fénix es falsa.
It was forged, Your Majesty!
Fue falsificada, Su Majestad.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad,
I've heard that the Phoenix Heart Tokens
he oído que la llave del corazón del fénix
were cast from the Phoenix Imperial Seal
fue hecha fundiendo
of Empress Wenxi.
el sello de la emperatriz Wenxi.
Though the carvings can be replicated,
El sello de la emperatriz tiene una textura especial.
the unique material of the Phoenix Imperial Seal
El grabado se puede falsificar,
cannot be faked.
pero la textura no.
Whether it's genuine or not,
Para saber si es auténtica o falsa,
we need only compare the two Phoenix Heart Tokens.
basta con comparar las dos llaves del corazón del fénix.
Cui Jun's, Prince Jing'an's.
La de Cui Jun, la del Rey Xiao.
And this one...
Y esta pieza...
This one belongs to Crown Prince Wenxi.
Esta es del Príncipe Heredero Wenxi.
The engraving on it
El grabado fue hecho
was carved by my mother herself.
por mi madre.
This one is the "Phoenix Head" token.
Esta es la cabeza del fénix,
It holds command over the other 3 Phoenix Heart Tokens.
y puede convocar a las otras tres llaves del corazón del fénix.
Are you truly willing to take out one of the tokens
¿De verdad vas a mostrar una llave del corazón del fénix
to play along with me in this act?
para hacer esto conmigo?
Right now, the world only knows of
Ahora el mundo solo conoce
the 2 tokens held by Cui Jun and my mother.
las dos en las manos de Cui Jun y de mi madre.
They have no idea that the rest are in your possession.
Pero no saben que las demás están en tu poder.
Once you reveal it,
Una vez que la muestres,
at the very least Grand Tutor and Li Mao will learn that
al menos el ministro Xie y Li Mao sabrán
Prince Jing'an was also a token holder.
que el Rey Xiao también es portador.
Your identity
Tu identidad
might be exposed.
podría quedar al descubierto.
What goes around comes around.
Que la causa tenga su efecto,
Debts of gratitude and vengeance must be repaid.
que la deuda se pague.
It's just a token, after all.
No es más que una insignia.
If it can bring the murderer to justice,
Si logra que el asesino sea castigado,
then it's worth it.
vale la pena.
It's indeed genuine.
Es verdadera.
No way.
¿Cómo es posible?
It was you.
Eres tú.
Xiao Wuyi, so you also have a Phoenix Heart Token.
Xiao Wuyi, resulta que también tienes la llave del corazón del fénix.
Princess Pingning,
Vizcondesa Pingning,
what do you mean by "also"?
¿qué significa "también"?
That Phoenix Heart Token is yours.
Esa llave del corazón del fénix es tuya.
You used your own token
Usaste tu llave del corazón del fénix
to help Jiayu frame me.
para ayudar a Jiayu a tenderme una trampa.
Princess Pingning,
Vizcondesa Pingning,
do you truly think I, Xiao Wuyi, am some kind of saint
¿realmente crees que yo soy un santo?
Everyone knows that
Como todos saben,
the Phoenix Heart Tokens contain secrets about hidden mineral deposits.
la llave del corazón del fénix contiene el secreto de las minas.
Tell me, which one of you here
¿Quién de los presentes
would not want them?
no la querría?
If I had a Phoenix Heart Token,
Si yo tuviera una llave del corazón del fénix,
why wouldn't I keep it hidden
¿por qué no la escondería bien
and secretly mine the resources?
y explotaría las minas en secreto,
Why would I bring it out in front of all the court officials
en lugar de mostrarla ante todos los ministros
just to frame you?
para acusarte a ti?
Who do you think you are?
¿Quién eres?
I'd like to ask all of you present:
Díganme, señores,
does anyone truly believe I, Xiao Wuyi,
¿alguien realmente cree que yo, Xiao Wuyi,
would be so selfless and generous?
sería tan generoso?
Your Majesty, besides the Phoenix Heart Token,
Su Majestad, además de la llave del corazón del fénix,
I also have a witness.
tengo un testigo.
Summon them.
Que pase.
This is Ms. Yang, the coachman's wife.
Yang, la esposa del mozo de cuadra, está aquí.
They saw nothing to begin with
Ellos no vieron nada.
and were no witnesses at all.
No son testigos.
But after you abducted them,
Pero después de que los secuestraste,
they ended up becoming witnesses against you.
se convirtieron en testigos.
She...
Ella...
She asked me where I was
Ella me preguntó dónde estaba yo
between 3 to 4 a.m. on the day of the incident,
al principio de la hora del tigre del día del incidente,
and whether I had been to the stable.
y si había ido a la cuadra.
After learning that I had not yet gotten up,
Cuando supo que todavía no me había levantado,
she asked no further questions.
no preguntó nada más.
That must've been the very hour you snuck into the stables
Esa era la hora en que entraste a la cuadra
to slip the poison, wasn't it?
a envenenar.
Let's go.
Vamos.
Wait.
Espera.
Don't commit any more killing.
No cometas más matanzas.
I really should've killed them all.
Hay que cortar el mal de raíz.
Princess Pingning murdered my mother
La Vizcondesa Pingning mató a mi madre
to seize the Phoenix Heart Token.
para robarle la llave del corazón del fénix.
Please seek justice for my mother, Your Majesty.
Su Majestad, pido justicia para mi madre.
These pieces of evidence are not enough to convict Lejun.
estas pruebas no son suficientes para condenar a Lejun.
Further investigation is needed.
Necesitamos investigarlo a fondo.
Please deliberate this matter with caution, Your Majesty.
Su Majestad, por favor, piénselo bien.
Prince Qi, are you trying
Príncipe Qi, ¿acaso
to cover up for Princess Pingning?
quieres encubrir a la Vizcondesa Pingning?
If Princess Pingning truly feels wronged,
Si la Vizcondesa Pingning se siente agraviada,
we might as well have the entire Eastern Palace thoroughly searched
que se investigue el Palacio Oriental
to prove her innocence.
para demostrar su inocencia.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
-Your Majesty! -I...
- ¡S.M. la Emperatriz Suprema! - Yo...
I plead guilty.
Me declaro culpable.
Lejun!
Lejun.
It was me.
Fui yo…
I murdered Princess Yunzhao
Fui yo quien mató a la condesa
to seize her Phoenix Heart Token.
para obtener su llave del corazón del fénix.
Please punish me, Your Majesty.
Su Majestad, por favor, castígueme.
He Tian.
He Tian.
Guards.
¡Guardias!
That day,
Ese día,
you suddenly had a stomachache and needed to lie down.
tu dolor de estómago repentino que te obligó a recostarte,
I was the one who drugged you.
fui yo quien te drogó.
What's wrong?
¿Qué pasa?
Mother,
Madre,
I feel a little unwell.
no me siento bien.
Your Highness, why don't we share a ride?
Condesa, ¿por qué no viaja conmigo?
I spared you
Solo porque
only because I did not wish to drag you into this.
no quise involucrarte.
If I had been ruthless enough
Si hubiera sido más despiadada
to strike directly at your carriage with Princess Yunzhao inside
y hubiera atacado directamente el carruaje de ustedes dos,
and send both of you to your deaths,
y hubieran muerto juntas,
none of this would have happened today, would it?
hoy no estaríamos así, ¿no?
Lejun!
¡Lejun!
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad,
Princess Yunzhao did not die as a criminal.
la condesa no murió por el pecado.
This token
Esta llave
was left to her by Empress Wenxi.
fue un legado de la emperatriz Wenxi para ella.
Now that she's passed away
Ya que ha fallecido
and had divorced Grand Tutor Xie,
y se divorció del Ministro Xie,
this token
esta llave
should rightfully be inherited by her offspring.
debería pasar a sus hijos.
So, according to you, Young Lord Xiao,
Heredero Xiao, en tu opinión,
-we should... -The whereabouts of the remaining
- debería... - No se sabe quién tiene el resto
Phoenix Heart Tokens are still unknown.
de las llave del corazón del fénix.
If Your Majesty were to claim them all for yourself
Ante todos los ministros,
in front of the entire court,
si usted quisiera quedárselas todas,
I'm afraid the remaining token holders
quizás los otros portadores
would never come forward.
nunca vuelvan a aparecer.
As for whether it should go to Grand Tutor Xie or Xie Jiayu—
¿Al Ministro Xie o a Xie Jiayu?
the choice is Your Majesty's.
Elija uno.
Come to me.
Ven a mi lado.
Good girl.
Buena chica.
You've really been through a lot.
Has sufrido mucho.
Your devotion to capturing the murderer who killed your mother
Atrapar al asesino por tu difunta madre
speaks volumes of your filial piety.
demuestra tu piedad filial.
This Phoenix Heart Token
Esta llave del corazón del fénix
was originally left to Princess Yunzhao by Empress Wenxi.
era de la emperatriz Wenxi para la condesa.
Now that she's passed away,
Ya que ella ha fallecido
it's only right that you keep it.
te corresponde a ti guardarla.
Thank you for your gracious kindness, Your Majesty.
Gracias, Su Majestad.
Should the secrets of the Phoenix Heart Token ever be uncovered,
Si en el futuro se descubre el secreto de la llave del corazón del fénix
I'll present this token to our great Ye without hesitation.
yo misma la entregaré a Ye.
What a good girl.
¡Qué buena chica!
From now on, come to the palace more often with Yuanji.
Ven al palacio con Yuanji a menudo.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Sí.
Xiao Wuyi.
Xiao Wuyi,
You forced me to personally send
me han obligado a enviar a mi propia hermana
my own sister to prison.
a la cárcel.
She committed murder,
Ella mató a alguien,
and the victim was none other than Xie Jiayu's mother.
y además a la madre de Xie Jiayu.
You know perfectly well why she did it.
Sabes por qué lo hizo.
She did it to protect me.
Ella lo hizo para protegerme.
Protect you?
¿Protegerte?
You both live in fear of Crown Prince Wenxi's return,
Ustedes tienen miedo de que aparezca el Príncipe Heredero Wenxi.
but Crown Prince Wenxi
Pero el Príncipe Heredero Wenxi
died 20 years ago!
murió hace 20 años.
If it weren't for Princess Yunzhao saving Li Lejun with her medical skills,
Si no hubiera sido por la medicina de la condesa,
Li Lejun's condition would never have improved,
la enfermedad de Li Lejun nunca se habría curado,
and she wouldn't have lived until now.
no habría vivido hasta ahora.
And yet, because of a little suspicion,
Por un poco de sospecha,
a fleeting fear,
un poco de miedo,
she could raise her blade against the very person who saved her.
ella pudo matar a su benefactora.
Tell me, did Li Lejun do nothing wrong?
¿No hizo mal Li Lejun?
Once she chose to act,
Ya que lo hizo,
she must bear the consequences.
tiene que asumir las consecuencias.
Li Yizhi, as the Regent,
Li Yizhi, como regente,
you're supposed to know right from wrong
debes saber qué está bien y qué está mal,
and where the line must be drawn!
y dónde está el límite.
Right from wrong?
¿Bien y mal?
Do you dare say that you helped Xie Jiayu
¿Te atreves a decir que ayudaste a Xie Jiayu
without any selfish motives?
sin ningún interés personal?
How insolent of you.
Eres demasiado arrogante.
You know how much I couldn't bear to part with Yaoyao.
Sabes cuánto me duele perder a Yaoyao,
Now that you've driven my sister into jail,
y ahora encarcelas a mi hermana,
you still expect me to continue being friends with you
¿todavía esperas que siga siendo tu amigo
and push forward with the reform together?
y que sigamos adelante con la reforma?
No such easy bargain exists
En este mundo,
in this world!
¡no hay nada tan bueno!
Your Highness Prince Qi!
Príncipe Qi,
If you must find someone to blame
si necesitas culpar a alguien
to make yourself feel better,
para sentirte mejor,
you can hate me.
puedes culparme a mí.
But Li Yizhi,
Pero Li Yizhi,
you, too, rose from the ranks of the displaced commoners.
tú también saliste de los refugiados.
Since you've chosen to sit in this position,
Ya que has decidido ocupar este trono,
you should have a more compassionate heart
debes tener un corazón más compasivo
and broader aspirations.
y una visión más amplia.
The road ahead is long.
El camino es largo,
Do not let fear and desire consume you
no dejes que el miedo y la codicia te dominen
and make you forget the path you once walked.
y te hagan olvidar de dónde vienes.
Is Crown Prince Wenxi
¿El Príncipe Heredero Wenxi
really dead?
realmente murió?
He's dead.
Murió.
He died long ago,
Murió hace mucho
and he'll never come back.
y nunca volverá.